<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>The Death of Charles Eyre Pascoe</title>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Compiled by </resp>
     <name>Lou Burnard</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Unpublished draft</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>Transcribed from the <title>Sutton and Cheam Advertiser,</title> 15 Nov 1912, page 5. (<ref
      target="https://www.newspapers.com/image/975619067/">facsimile</ref>)</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2026-05-22">Tagged in TEI and exposed on Digital Lacy website</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <front>
   <p>Pascoe's death was unexpected, and somewhere between tragedy and farce. There is a full
    account in the local newspaper, the <title>Sutton and Cheam Advertiser</title> for 15 November
    1912, p.5. The story was picked up widely (presumably because of the dog) by the provincial
    press: very similar short versions of it appearing in (at least) the <title>Yorkshire Evening
     Argus</title>, the <title>Worcestershire Chronicle</title>, the <title>Leicester
     Mercury</title>, the <title>Newcastle Daily Chronicle</title>, the <title>Leicester
     Chronicle</title>, <title>The Citizen</title>, the <title>Evening Gazette</title>, the
     <title>Western Daily Press</title> and the <title>Huddersfield Daily Examiner</title>. It is
    noticed in the <title>Westminster Gazette</title> (according to Wikipedia), but I have found no
    mention of it in any other national paper. </p>
  </front>
  <body>
   <head>Barking of Dogs and sudden Death.</head>
   <head> Sad End of well-known resident of Wallington. </head>
   <p> Mr. Charles Eyre Pascoe, who was a well-known author, and lived at Penwerris,
    Hillside-gardens, Wallington, met with a sudden and tragic death last Saturday afternoon not
    many yards from his house. For a long time the barking of dogs had been his special aversion,
    and his feeling about it was so strong that he had written several letters of protest to the
    local Press. Probably the noise had more effect on him than it would have had on another because
    he had been in ill health for some time. Last Saturday afternoon he was lying on the couch after
    having had something to eat, and was trying to go to sleep when he heard the barking of a dog a
    few doors away. Finding where it was he got up in a state of excitement and hurried to the front
    door of Cabana, the residence of a lady named Mrs. Lawrence to complain and ask that the dog
    should be quieted. The hurry and the excitement made it difficult for him to speak, but Mrs.
    Lawrence understood what he meant to say and said that she was very sorry and would see what she
    could do about it. She noticed that he seemed ill and very kindly asked him to come inside and
    sit down for a little while so that be might recover. Mr. Pascoe accepted her offer, and was
    crossing the threshold when he stumbled and fell, and died before help could be obtained. With
    the assistance ot her mother-in-law and a gentleman who was passing she got him in doors, and
    herself went for Dr. McDougall. He came at once, but could do nothing, as life was already
    extinct. </p>
   <p> Mr. Pascoe, who was 70 years of age, was a journalist and author. Among the books he wrote
    was one concerning the associations of Charles Dickens with Yorkshire, which showed a careful
    study of all possible sources of information, and had a good reception on its publication.
    Another dealt with the history of the most famous street in the world—Downing-street. This was a
    very successful volume, and is regarded as an authority on the subject. Locally Mr. Pascoe was
    very well known, and had many friends, and among the societies to which he belonged was the ‘
    House of Commons,” though he had not attended there lately. </p>
   <p> He was the son of Major Pascoe, of the Royal Marines, who saw active service in the French
    and American Wars. He was educated at Christ’s Hospital and was ten years in the Admiralty. In
    1869 he retired on a commuted pension, and took up journalism, and in the next year he got
    married and went to America, where he joined the staff of the “Boston Globe” as foreign editor.
    After three years he returned to England, and acted as London correspondent for several American
    nowspapers. Among the work he did was an investigation of the English prison system for the “New
    York Journal.” Later he joined the staff of “The Standard,” and wrote for that paper some
    striking articles on canal life. During his latter years he wrote several books, including the
    two already mentioned. </p>
   <p> An inquest was held on the body at Bandon Hill on Tuesday afternoon by Mr. F. J. Nightingale,
    Coroner for the Reigate Division. </p>
   <p> Mrs. Pascoe, the widow, said that her husband was 70 years of age, and was not very robust,
    having suffered slightly from a weak heart. But he had not been seen by a doctor very recently.
    On Saturday afternoon a dog at Cabana was barking, and it seemed to excite him a good deal. He
    was on the sofa trying to sleep, but the barking made him nervous and he got up and went out,
    intending, as she believed, to complain about the noise to the owner of the dog. Mrs. Pascoe
    thought he hurried. along to the house, and she understood that he died there, </p>
   <p> Mrs. Helen Agnes White Lewrence, of Cabana, Hillside-gardens, said that on Saturday afternoon
    Mr. Pascoe came to her door and complained about the dog barking. She said she was very sorry
    and would try to stop it. Deceased seemed excited and had great difficulty in speaking at all,
    which fact might have been due to the excitement of hurrying. He seemed out of breath, and,
    seeing that he looked rather ill, she asked him if he would like to come in and sit down. He
    started to cross the threshold, but had only taken a few steps when he fell down. Witness called
    her mother-in-law and a gentleman passing came to their assistance, and the deceased was carried
    indoors. Dr. McDougall also came at her request. </p>
   <p> By the foreman of the jury—The dog was in the garden. </p>
   <p> Dr. W. S. McDougall, of Woodcote-road, Wallington, said he had known Mr. Pascoe for many
    years, but did not think that he had ever attended him professionally. He was summoned on
    Saturday afternoon by Mrs. Lawrencs, and later he made an examination of the body, when he found
    that heart was ruptured. Death must have been instantaneous. </p>
   <p> Asked by the Coroner whether death was caused by hurrying to the spot and the excitement, the
    doctor replied that in his opinion it was. </p>
   <p> The jury returned a verdict of “Death from natural causes.” </p>
   <p> The funeral took place at Bandon Hill Cemetery on Wedneday. The burial rites were conducted
    by the Rev. R.J. Doble, and the mourners were Mrs Pascoe, Mr Wheeler, Miss Gammell, Mr and Mrs
    Gurdon Palin, Mr and Mrs Arthur Barnard, Mr and Mrs Denny, Mr and Mrs Leman Harem, Miss Heeley
    and Mrs. Poole. There were no flowers by special request. </p>
   <div>
    <head>Other notices</head>

    <p><label>WORRIED BY DOG'S BARK.</label> Whilst complaining to a neighbour about the barking of
     her dog, Mr. C. E. Pascoe, journalist and author, of Wallington, fell dead on the threshold of
     the door. A doctor said Mr. Pascoe’s heart was very weak, and in his opinion the heart was
     ruptured through becoming excited over the barking of the dog. The jury returned a verdict of
     death from natural causes. (<title>The Citizen</title>, Nov. 13 1912, p. 5) </p>

    <p> While complaining to a neighbour about the barking of her dog, Mr. C. E. Pascoe, journalist
     and author, of Wallington, fell dead on the threshold of the door. At the inquest on Tuesday,
     it was stated that Mr. Pascoe, who had a weak heart, had been annoyed for a long time by dogs
     barking. (<title>Huddersfield Daily Examiner</title>, Nov 13 1912, p.3) </p>

    <p><label>AUTHOR'S FATAL EXCITEMENT </label> The barking of dogs near his house, it was stated
     at an inquest yesterday at Wallington (Surrey) on Mr Charles Eyre Pascoe, an author, had
     worried him for some time past, and on Saturday he became very excited at the barking of a
     neighbour's dog and went to its owner to complain. Noticing that he looked ill, the neighbour
     asked him to come indoors and sit down, but while he was crossing the threshold he fell dead. A
     doctor said Mr. Pascoe's heart was very weak, and in his opinion the heart was ruptured through
     becoming excited over the barking of the dogs. The jury returned a verdict of "Death from
     natural causes." (<title>South Wales Echo</title>, 13 Nov 1912, p.4) </p>
    <p>A well-known man of letters and a graceful versifier has passed away in the person of Mr.
     Charles Eyre Pascoe, who for many years was a familiar figure in Bohemian circles. There were
     few men who knew their London better than Mr. Pascoe, and still fewer who would treat of its
     history in at once so interesting and informing a manner. In the course of the years many
     delightful little works on London had come from his pen. (<title>Southern Daily Echo,</title>
     16 Nov 1912, p.2) </p>
    <!--This appeared in the Morning Post letters in 1883 - a bit early for Pascoe, but it's the sort of thing he might well have written
  <p>DOGS.
TO THE EDITOR OF THE MORNING POST.</p>
<p>
Sir,—‘ Let dogs delight to bark and bite.” Certainly ;
but not in London. It is bad enough to have your ears
tormented all day long with street music, without the
extra nuisance of your neighbours’ dogs barking, as well as
the annoyance of a pavement unfit to walk upon. People
who live in large cities must consult the convenience of
others as well as their own pleasure, or they become a
public nuisance.—I am, sir, yours, &c.,</p>
<p> March 30. ONE OF THE COMMUNITY.</p>
 -->
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
