<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Selected letters from Charles Eyre Pascoe</title>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Compiled by </resp>
     <name>Lou Burnard</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Unpublished draft</p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <p>Derived mostly from the British Library Newspapers Online database.</p>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2026-05-28">Tagged in TEI and exposed on Digital Lacy website</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>

  <front>
   <p> </p>
  </front>
  <body>
   <div>


    <head>THE RECEPTION OF THE BELGIANS,</head>
    <head>To the Editor of the Royal Cornwall Gazette</head>
    <p>Sir, – Will you permit me through the medium of your valuable paper to bring under the notice
     of Cornishmen the claims of the Belgian Reception Committee to public support, for I regret to
     say that up to the present time, although nearly every county in England has responded to the
     appeal made by the committee for funds, yet Cornwall singularly holds aloof. In October last
     the Belgian Guard Civique – a body in some respects answering to our volunteers– invited the
     English volunteers to Brussels. Over eleven hundred from all parts of England availed
     themselves of that invitation. Ministers of State, the army, the municipal authorities, and the
     people generally came forward and helped in purse and person to welcome our volunteers, and the
     King and Queen, sympathising with their subjects, in the most lavishly hospitable manner
     entertained the guests of the Guard Civique ; one and all displayed a hearty desire to
     fraternise with the English, and to draw more closely the bonds which unite the two nations.
     The Belgians made the invitation given by their Guard Civique a national movement, and the
     return invitation by the volunteers of England should be, and I believe to a great extent is,
     looked upon in tho same light. </p>
    <p>Personally, I have not the honour to belong to tho volunteer service, but not the less had I
     reason to admire the noble and enthusiastic manner in which our volunteers were received by the
     entire Belgian nation, and as a Cornishman I feel that it does not reflect great credit on a
     county noted for its hospitality that it should bo the last to respond to the appeal of the
     reception committee. Surely, sir, the people of England will not prove themselves less
     enthusiastic in such a movement than the Belgians did. It must not be said that we are
     behind-hand in hospitality, and that there is a difficulty in raising funds sufficient to
     entertain the representatives of a nation who positively loaded our people with honour. This is
     not, I maintain, sir, a volunteer movement essentially. In Brussels, the King, the Ministers of
     State, the public bodies, found the funds – not the Guard Civique– the Belgians considered the
     invitation (though given by their Guard Civique) as national, and affecting their national
     honour, and I do trust that the Cornish people will yet heartily reeiprocrate that feeling.</p>
    <p> I shall have much pleasure in taking charge of any subscriptions that may be forwarded to
     me, which I will acknowledge and hand over to Captain Mackenzie, of the London Scottish, the
     hon. treasurer to the Reception Fund. – </p>
    <signed>Your obedient servant, CHARLES EYRE PASCOE, Admiralty, Somerset House, London, W.C, May
     Bth,</signed>
    <note>
     <bibl><title>Royal Cornwall Gazette</title>. (May 16, 1867) Issue 3331, p.6</bibl></note>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>American Payments to English Authors</head>
    <p>PERHAPS the following facts may have an interest for English authors whose works are
     occasionally reprinted in America without their leave and without compensation. The other day I
     received a letter from a firm of Boston publishers asking me if I would ascertain the address
     of a certain English author whose books are published anonymously, because, wrote they, ‘we
     want to pay her something.’ Being naturally solicitous that this message of conciliation and
     justice should reach the author as speedily as possible, I enclosed a stamped unaddressed
     letter to him (or her) in a letter to his (or her) London publisher. I waited some little time
     for a reply, and not receiving any acknowledgment one way or the other, I wrote again to the
     London publisher. I said that I had ventured to trouble him with my former letter, <hi>which
      had reference to the payment of some money</hi>, because. at the moment, I knew of no better
     way of reaching the author, and that if my letter had not been forwarded, I might consider the
     propriety of publishing an advertisement in the Atheneum, This elicited a reply, saying, ‘The
     author is at present abroad, and will no doubt send an answer to your note if he considers one
     necessary ; but having <hi>many similar ones </hi>[the italics are mine] <hi>from other people,
      he may not feel called upon to do so.</hi>’ </p>
    <p> This last paragraph is so rich that I ask permission to submit it to your consideration. It
     appears to be a fact that there is at least one English author in existence who can boast
     receiving ‘many’ letters having reference to the payment of American copyright money, and who
     can afford to ignore them. It is hardly of much interest to your readers to know that, though
     acting as ‘literary agent” in England for the Boston firm in question, I am no more answerable
     for what English books they publish than the man in the moon. I am as earnest an advocate of
     international copyright as their honesty in this case leads me to hope they are; and whenever
     the opportunity has served during the past twelve years, I have done my utmost with them and
     others in America to insist on the right of the English author to a fair measure of
     compensation. Perhaps, after all, the London publisher may have misjudged his client. I shall
     rest in hope. </p>
    <signed>CHARLES EYRE PASCOE</signed>
    <note>
     <bibl> “American Payments to English Authors” letter in <title>The Athenaeum.</title> (Nov 8,
      1884): p 592 Iss. 2976/</bibl>
    </note>
   </div>
   <div>

    <head>The Theatres</head>
    <p> Mr. Pascoe, author of the “Dramatic List” and other well-known publications, sends us the
     following note regarding a grievance which, judging from the letters we receive from time to
     time, is widely felt by a large and important section of the play-going public: </p>
    <p> Is this a subject you would draw attention to? I feel sure it is one of some interest to
     many. In these times of co-operation and cheap trading, is there no manager of a London theatre
     wise and enterprising enough to conciliate the interests of a very large section of the
     middle-class—the hard-working and thrifty? The most of that class rise early and go to bed
     early, and live in the suburbs. It ordinarily dines at six and gets to bed about 11. Moreover,
     it can afford a few pounds a year, for amusements and holidays. Because Mayfair, which neither
     toils nor spins, turns night into day, and chooses to dine when all sensible folk are thinking
     of going to bed, no inconsiderable section of this middle-class is debarred going to the
     theatres. The stall régime, for which we have to thank Mr Bancroft, is becoming an intolerable
     nuisance. The managers seem to think there is no public outside of Mayfair, and we of liberal
     tendencies (as to our shillings for the play) and of Home Rule influences suburbwise are,
     forsooth, compelled to accept an alien form of government most foreign to our tastes. We have
     to pay 10s. for a stall when 6s. are amply sufficient; to wait till 6.15 for our play when 7.30
     is a reasonable hour for its commencement; and to be content to get to bed at 1 when 11 is an
     hour beyond which a wise man will not wish to be kicking his heels about outside of it. Who
     will rise and deliver us from this aristocratic thraldom? What has Mayfair to do with Putney
     that it should be thus dictated to by an oligarchy of voluptuous diners at eight, with which,
     Conservative, alas! as it is, Putney should have no affinity, Our ancestors, whose rule it
     would conserve, dined early and went to bed early, and got home from the theatre at 10. </p>
    <signed>- I am, &amp;c., Charles E. Pascoe. </signed>
    <note><bibl>"The Theatres" [quotes a letter from CEP] <title>Daily News</title>, (June 7, 1886)
      Iss. 12529</bibl>
    </note>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>[The Maybrick Case: against the Verdict]</head>
    <p>[From some out of the enormous number of letters ... respecting the Maybrick case, we give
     the following extracts] ... </p>
    <p>Mr. Charles Eyre Pascoe:-&quot; Most of your correspondents give the go-bye to the point, is
     there `reasonable doubt’? That, as it seems to me (and to thousands of others doubtless), is
     the all-important question. The majority with whom I have discussed the case say there is. If
     misfortune had placed me on the jury, having carefully read the whole of the evidence and the
     judge's summing up in your columns, I should have stuck to that point, and said there is. Mr.
     Donald Nicoll’s letter is but one of many that might be a written touching the fallibility of
     judges and jurors. There was the case in 1884 of Siddle and Lowson condemned to death at the
     Durham Assizes. Siddle emphatically swore to his innocence throughout. The jury found both
     prisoners guilty. I have no reason, notwithstanding your assertions, said the judge in passing
     sentence, to entertain <hi>the smallest doubt</hi> – [the italics are mine] – that the jury has
     come to a right and conscientious verdict. But Siddle was found to be innocent, was reprieved,
     and received a free pardon. My father took arsenic on his own account for gouty complaint, He
     was induced to do so by a book sent to him by an old and valued friend. I well remember the
     protests of my mother, and, let me add, our own family doctor. But my father persisted, and was
     cured. A `valetudinarian dyspeptic’ will take almost anything to alleviate his sufferings,
     about which doctors know as little as medical students. They mostly laugh at them. (I wonder
     whether Carlyle had recourse to doctors to alleviate his). Then the dyspeptic doctors himself,
     and will doctor himself in face of all the Physicians in the world, because he finds, from
     years of experience of many, that they do him no good. It is, I submit not unreasonable to give
     credit to Mrs. Maybrick's statements concerning the `the beef juice. As for the `sick unto
     death,' a wife knows more of her husbands ailments and previous sufferings and constitutional
     weaknesses than many a physician. To hang a woman because she wrote these words would be
     murder. </p>
    <note><bibl>
      <title>Daily News </title>(Aug 13, 1889) Iss. 13526, p.2 </bibl>
    </note>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>A WORD FOR THE SKIPPER</head>
    <!-- https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SS_Drummond_Castle-->
    <p>. Sir, – It was almost a foregone conclusion as to what the judgment in the case of the
     Drummond Castle would be. It commends itself to the common sense of all who have had experience
     of ships or travelled the ocean. Your leader in to-day&#39;sissue tempts one to contribute my
     humble word of agreement to all you say. But in doing so, all my personal sympathy lies with
     the skipper. He is expected by his directors to make himself courteous and attentive to the
     passengers. That order stands among his "confidential" directions. Now, in the Atlantic trade,
     for example, it has become a custom to hold a saloon concert on behalf of the Liverpool
     Seamen&#39;s Orphanage at the end of almost every voyage. Tho passengers look for the presence
     and support of the captain on these occasions. The captain himself can hardly hold aloof, if he
     would. I do not know of any more difficult position to fill than that of skipper of an ocean
     steamship, in which a seamain&#39;s sense of duty and responsibility is oftimes very nearly in
     conflict with his directors&#39; desire to keep the goodwill and support of their company&#39;s
     passengers. Only those who are behind the scenes know of the frivolous and vexatious complaints
     concerning captains, officers, and stewards carried to the manager&#39;s ears by thoughtless
     and irresponsible travellers. These complaints are too often listened to than not. The
     complainants, for the most part, have not the smallest notion of the grave responsibilities and
     arduous duties captains are frequently called upon to fulfil. Many passengers seem to think
     that he should be at their beck and call to dance attendance on them on the deck, to tell funny
     stories in the saloon, or to answer any and every silly question they may please to put to him.
     If he shows a disposition to keep to his cabin and hold to his legitimate duties he is voted
     the very reverse of what he is. I have made my sixteenth ocean trip; and I may confidently say
     that the only occasions when I have felt nervous at sea have been when the skipper&#39;s
     attention to his passengers have been more marked than his presence on the bridge.-</p>
    <signed>Yours faithfully, CHARLES EYRE PASCOE.</signed>
    <note><bibl>“A word for the skipper” <title>Daily News</title> (July 30, 1896) Issue
      15706</bibl></note>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head> A LITERARY LONDONER IN LIVERPOOL. _</head>
    <head> A HINT TO AMERICAN VISITORS</head>
    <p> Mr. Charles Eyre Pascoe, author of “London of To-day," writes as follows :-— </p>
    <p> Sir,—A week or two ago I happened to be in Liverpool. Your famous city presents many points
     of interest to person intent on business, but those points may be said to decrease in
     proportion as he reflects on pleasure. Holiday makers hardly hanker after docks, shipping, and
     seamen. Yet I do not know one city in England offering so many inducements at this summer
     season of the year to the haphasard traveller to sojourn within its borders for a while as
     Liverpool. It affords so many cheap, convenient, daily facilities for inland and seaward
     excursions as to lead a Londoner to envy the opportunities of its citizens. Apparently,
     Liverpool makes no boast of its superior attractions this way, for it does little to-day to
     encourage the stranger to tarry, take note of them, and turn them to account. </p>
    <p> Time was when every Atlantic liner contributed its handsome summer quota of passengers to
     Liverpool's hotels. That time is gone. Local Liverpool knows it and apparently folds its hands
     with a kind of sleepy complacency. The Cunard Company and the White Star Company are nothing if
     not go-ahead and up-to-date. ‘They and the North-Western Railway Company have, so to say,
     tapped and drawn off the local American trade. This was inevitabic, for Southampton still
     stands where it did, and Sir Charles Scotter rules the South-Western road with energy. </p>
    <p> Such ships as the Campania and Teutonic now run along the Prince's Landing-stage ; a couple
     of gangways fore and aft are hoisted out; down one glide the mails and down the other walk the
     passengers ; and within the space of an hour both are on their way to London by special trains
     from the very point of disembarkation. What few Transatlantic tourists the greater or lesser
     liners turn into the city may generally be found at the Adelphi Hotel. In that respect they
     show a wise discretion, for in the category of British hotels, metropolitan or provincial,
     little or great, old or modern, there is none, in my humble opinion, that excels the Adelphi in
     Liverpool for solid comfort, excellence of living and able administration. It is a model hotel
     worthy of being studied by whatsoever company, syndicate, or bold proprietor seeks a dividend
     at the business of hotel-keeping. As to its style of living, that might be studied with very
     great advantage to their customers by four-fifths of the hotel keepers and restaurateurs of
     London. </p>
    <p> In June we shall be in the thick of the American tourist season. The Cunard Company and the
     White Star are sending their splendid ships out of New York and Boston filled with
     holiday-makers : good Americans who come to spend a couple of summer months in England, to see
     what may be seen, and to enjoy themselves generally. </p>
    <p> My immediate purpose in asking you to publish this letter (if haply it may be read by
     Americans) is to advise some of them, sufficiently leisure- loving, let’s hope, when they come
     to England to pause in their present too rapid flight onward to London. I venture to say on
     behalf of Liverpool what Liverpool will not venture to say for itself, that it excels London --
     namely, in many respects as a place of sojourn with a view to inexpensive, varied, and
     exceedingly attractive excursions, to wit, into Wales, to the North of Ireland, to the Isle of
     Man, to the Lake District, and into that rarely beautiful Midland county—Derby- shire.</p>
    <p> I do not know, for example, one part of England st once so charming and invigorating as that
     of which Matlock Bath is the centre. Ite beauties are unbounded, its opportunities of easy
     excursions almost limitiess. It has two excellent hotels which for picturesque setting are not
     to be matched—the Royal Bath and the New Bath hotels. I take leave to warrant the comforts of
     both, having but lately having had experience of them, to which fair warranty I hereunto append
     my name. Practical experiences are far more useful than theoretical opinions. From May 6 to May
     12 I stayed in Liverpool at the Adelphi ; from May 13 to 16 at the Royal Bath, Matlock. My
     moderate bill for rooms and board was duly met on presentation. From Liverpool I excursionised
     to Llandudno, Beaumaris, Isle of Man, Londonderry, and the nearer parts of Cheshire : from
     Matlock Bath I went to Rowsley, to Miller's Dale, to Darley Dale, to Chatsworth, Haddon Hali,
     Buxton—I know not where, in a district full of beauty. And I was back in London within ten
     days. If there be any Americans now landing in Liverpool, trudging along unknowing what they
     seek, let them follow in my path, and I'll lay a wager that they'll not regret having road this
     contribution from their obedient servant, </p>
    <signed>CHARLES EYRE PASCOE.</signed>
    <note><bibl>“A literary Londoner in Liverpool” letter to <title>Liverpool Daily Post</title>, 25
      May 1896, p.7</bibl>
    </note>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>IS IT FACT OR FLOURISH OF PHRASES?</head>
    <p> Sir,—The latest newspapers from Boston devote columns to the reception given in that city to
     Mr. Bryan, Democratic candidate for the Presidency. Among other things he was of course
     entertained to dinner. While he was eating a hasty meal, a gentleman representing the
     Bimetallic Union of Boston delivered himself of what he called “a non-partisan welcome" in
     which he said: <quote> Already the lovers of liberty throughout the world are making the cable
      hot with messages to you as a great emancipator of nations. The agriculturists of all Europe
      ask you to strike the blow, and they will follow your lead in restoring prices with the free
      coinage of silver. Seven hundred members of England's Parliament, with Balfour at the head,
      honour your mission. Grenfell, the multi millionaire chairman of tho bimetallic committee of
      England, sends greeting a column long to the "New York Journal" and says were he in America he
      would be proud to wear the Bryan button: and Bismarck, the creator of the German Empire, who
      has seen the prices of labour cut down one half by deminting silver, asks your to break the
      fetters of Europe, and promises Europe will follow. </quote>
    </p>
    <p> It would be very interesting to some of us on this side to know if this be fact or mere
     flourish of phrases. I have talked with a good many people on the subject of Mr Bryan's
     candidature, and may safely say that, as yet, not one single average middle-class Englishman to
     whom I have spoken understands what Bimetallism is. And now we learn that "700 members of
     England's Parliament" -- thirty, by the way, more than sit in the House of Commons, so, some of
     them must be Peers—honour Mr Bryan's mission (whatever that may mean), which is at least a kind
     of wishing him well in his efforts to turn the financial system of the world topsy-turvy.—
     Yours faithfully, London, CHARLES EYRE PASCOE.</p>
    <note><bibl>“Is it fact or flourish of phrases?” letter to <title>Daily News</title>, (Oct 15
      1896) Issue 15772, p.3</bibl>
    </note>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>[The Transvaal Crisis]</head>
    <p> Sir,—That reference of Sir Edward Clarke's to Majuba Hill should be protested against by
     every fair-minded journal in the Kingdom. It is an outrage on the honest desire to be just and
     fair of every earnest-minded, thoughtful Englishman. I have been travelling about England a
     great deal of late, and have talked with all sorts and conditions of men on this very grave
     subject—only lately, with a well-known and prominent citizen of Leeds, Conservative in
     politics. L have not spoken with one who has not earnestly and thoughtfully recognised the
     gravity of the Transvaal business, nor with one who has so much as once alluded to the subject
     of “Majuba Hill,” or to any suggestion or desire to wipe out the stain of that defeat. It is my
     belief that not one Englishman of any thoughtfulness, or capacity and judgment, in ten desires
     to proceed against the Boers with sword and fire. What every Englishman wishes to do, and hopes
     the Government will do, is to settle once and for all the interminable dispute with Mr. Kruger,
     and to stop a course of conduct on the Boers’ part which every man I have spoken to who has had
     any experience of the Transvaal—and I have talked with friends and relations who have lived
     there—says is simply intolerable, and no longer to be borne by one proud of and honoured in
     bearing the name of Englishman. That's the point, Sir, with the average of us, Conservative or
     Liberal, and no other; and, as for “Majuba Hill," Sir Edward Clarke is utterly misinformed and
     mast be referring to a class of young English “Boer” who, happily for us, is of no sort of
     weight in expressing the real opinion of honest Englishmen.— </p>
    <signed>Yours faithfully, CHARLES EYRE PASCOE. Streatham, S.W. </signed>
    <note>
     <bibl><title>Daily News,</title> 30 Sept 1899</bibl>
    </note>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>[The Transvaal Crisis]</head>
    <p>Sir. -- Truly one grows infinitely weary of the preachers from the house-tops. The fire is
     burning from below; and when we look up for instructions practical and to the purpose all that
     we get are words, words, words. It is amazing to me, Sir, that you have the patience just now
     to print some of the letters which occupy your space. It is as if one were to ho to some man of
     ripe experience and judgment to solicit his advice on a matter of great urgency and importance,
     and he met your request for immediate help in the matter in hand with a long-winded
     argumentative sermon on some points in the Church Catechism. What in the name of common sense
     has the present condition of things in Natal, Cape Colony, and the Transvaal to do with the
     "Gospel of Quietism," or for that matter any known gospel at all? The fact is very evident that
     we are at war -- and that it is a very serious war, too. The one point, then, that concerns us
     just now is how best and soonest to win. Every man but a knave or a fool, must see that once
     the Boer ultimatum was delivered we had but one of two courses open to us, either (1) to cry
     "Peccavi!" and bring our troops and transports back to Britain, in which case we should, as a
     matter of course, have lost our South African Colonies or (2) to fight to the bitter end, as we
     propose to do now.</p>
    <p>As to what brought about this war, or who actually provoked it, is of no more interest at
     this juncture. I submit, than, Mr Harold Hare's experiences of the charms of the Gospel of
     Quietism. Nor (not to seem impertinent) is it of the slightest interest to the great majority
     of Englishmen, Scotsmen, and Irish men as to what are the particular views of this man or of
     that on the question of how far we can fulfil today the Divine precepts of the Sermon on the
     Mount. If a man waylays you with a bludgeon and threatens to kill you, it is your duty to the
     commonwealth as a citizen to try to protect yourself and to give the assailant over to the
     charge of the nearest constable. If Mr Silas Hocking, Mr. Stead, and Mr Page-Hopps, and those
     that think and act with them., fancy for a moment that their countrymen are likely to turn
     their backs to the Boers and to cry "Dear Christian friends kill, slay, destroy, rob, do as you
     will, I am your brother," they and their followers had best apply for present admission through
     the rightful authority, to the nearest lunatic asylum of their county. Having the courage of my
     opinions, as Christian, I hope, and as a Liberal, I am sure, I beg to sign my name,
     respectfully CHARLES EYRE PASCOE, Streatham, S.W.</p>
    <note>
     <bibl> <title>Daily News</title>, Dec 30 1899, p.9;</bibl>
    </note>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>[Conclusion of a letter from Silas Hocking, in response to the foregoing]</head>
    <p>.... Mr. Charles Eyre Pascoe “hopes" that he is Liberal and a Christian. Well, I hope so,
     too; but why one Liberal should object to another Liberal thinking for himself, or expressing
     his thoughts, I do not understand. Perhaps this is the new Liberalism we have heard so much
     about lately. Mr. Charles Eyre Pascoe’s Christianity is so large and generous that he would
     like to see me locked up in a lunatic asylum. After this gentlemanly method of conducting a
     controversy I do not wonder he says, “I beg to sign my name respectfully." Mr. Charles Eyre
     Pascoe's Christianity is not only large and generous, but delightfully latitudinarian. “‘What
     in the name of common-sense,"’ he asks, “has the present condition of things in Natal, Cape
     Colony, and the Transvaal to do with the gospel of ‘ Quiet ism,’ or, for that matter, with any
     known gospel at all?’’ Exactly; the gospel appears to be of no account to-day. The ethics of
     the New Testament are in the way when Christians are thirsting for blood. Any suggestion of
     peace makes Mr. Pascoe impatient, and he wonders at the patience of the Editor; but people who
     are so certain they are right ought not to be impatient, and a man who hopes he is Liberal and
     a Christian ought to have charity. It is little chance the minority has to-day of uttering its
     protest, and so the majority need not be churlish about the matter. </p>
    <p> One thing, however, seems clear. The tide in England is turning. We have been trapped by
     inept diplomacy, hoodwinked by adventurers, blinded by an unreasoning passion, and led astray
     by those whom we trusted as our guides. And we are slowly awaking to the fact. It is no wonder,
     perhaps, that the bulk of Englishmen are angry and resentfui, and are casting round for a
     scapegoat, but they should not hurl their brickbats at those who have protested from the first
     that the war was unecesary, and therefore a crime. Let them go for the real makers of the
     mischief—Messrs. Chamberlain, Rhodes, and Milner. Those who havc pleaded for peace instead of
     war, for arbitration instead of the sword, need not fear the verdict of time. If, however, to
     preach the gospel of righteousness and brotherhood and goodwill be a crime, I am prepared to
     abide by the consequences.—</p>
    <signed>I am, yours truly, Highgate, N. SILAS K. HOCKING.</signed>
    <note><bibl><title>Daily News</title> 1 Jan 1900, p.6 </bibl>
    </note>
   </div>
   <div>
    <head>[Pascoe's response to the foregoing]</head>
    <p> Sir,—It is evident that the Rev. Silas Hocking is not to be pinned down to the plain
     consideration of a plain question, which, if you will allow me, I will put in this way:
     Supposing we are passengers in a ship on fire in a great storm at sea, which is the best to be
     done, to utter a silent, heartfelt prayer to the Almighty for pardon and courage, and turn to
     and help the ship’s company to get the fire under, and the ship under control, or to call a
     meeting in the saloon to discuss the cause of the calamity and the Law of Storms, and the
     question of whether we should bend to every trouble and difficulty that assails us, or yet
     trusting in God, rise up and gird ourselves like men and strive to overcome our trouble and
     difficulty? Mr. Hocking invites us to a conference, where we shall probably get little else but
     speeches and talk, talk and speeches, with possibly invective against the Government. Well,
     what I maintain, in defiance of Mr. Hocking, is, that just at this moment we want much less
     talk and far more quiet thought and well planned action. We shall be pleased to attend Mr.
     Hocking and his conference by and by, when the storm is abated and the fire under. Then,
     perhaps, wo may be found to agree in a variety of matters, political and religious, Meanwhile,
     I am still living in hope that I am a Christian by persuasion, and a good Liberal too; albeit
     my angry passions will arise when I find other Christians and other Liberals inviting us to
     meetings to hear their speeches when we desire to be otherwise occupied in any capacity,
     however humble, that may be helpful to our country at present engaged in a very serious and
     terrible war. May I add this—I did not say I would like to see Mr. Hocking in a lunatic asylum.
     God forbid. I hope he will enjoy mental quiet and every happiness to the last hour of his life,
     and that ho may help us also to get what measure we can of both at this particular moment, by
     sparing us further consideration of his sermons, at all events in the newspapers. I hope to be
     allowed again to subscribe myself, respectfully yours (and his, if he will), CHARLES EYRE
     PASCOE Streatham, Jan. 1st </p>
    <note>
     <bibl><title>Daily News</title>, 3 Jan 1900, p.3</bibl></note>
   </div><div><head>[The sort of letter Pascoe may well have written]</head>
    <head>DOGS.
     TO THE EDITOR OF THE MORNING POST.</head>
    <p>
     Sir,—‘ Let dogs delight to bark and bite.” Certainly ;
     but not in London. It is bad enough to have your ears
     tormented all day long with street music, without the
     extra nuisance of your neighbours’ dogs barking, as well as
     the annoyance of a pavement unfit to walk upon. People
     who live in large cities must consult the convenience of
     others as well as their own pleasure, or they become a
     public nuisance.—I am, sir, yours, &amp;c.,</p>
    <p> March 30. ONE OF THE COMMUNITY.</p> <note><bibl><title>Morning Post</title>, 1883</bibl></note></div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
